Guide to the Papers of Jan Schilt
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Papers of Jan Schilt,
1931-1963
Schilt, Jan, b. 1894.
23.5 linear ft (ca.13,500 items in 27 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library
4079816
Biographical Note
Astronomer and administrator. Schilt was Rutherford Professor Emeritus at Columbia, invented the Schilt photometer, and helped clarify the motions of stars in the Milky Way. He was director of the Yale-Columbia Southern Station in Johannesburg and Canberra, Australia. He served as chairperson of Columbia's department of astronomy from 1936 until 1962.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Schilt's correspondence as chairperson of Columbia's department of astronomy and director of the Yale-Columbia Southern Station as well as the Rutherford Observatory at Columbia. The majority of arranged office files are comprised of memoranda, documents, some departmental correspondence, committee reports, course material including material for student laboratory exercises. Thers is also a small sampling of Schilt's early notes as a student and reports of oo-site testing done under the auspices of the National Science Foundation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Arranged Correspondence
Series II: Committees and Course Materials
Series III: Lab Materials
Series IV: Early Notes of Schilt
Series V: Testing Materials
Subjects
Columbia University.--Observatory.; Columbia University.--Dept. of Astronomy.; Astrometry.; Astronomical observatories.; Astronomical observatories--Administration.; Astronomy.; Astrophysics.; Photometry.; Documents.; Exercises.; Memorandums.; Notes.; Office files.; Reports.; Astronomers.; College administrators.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
02/23/89 M-89-2-23 astronomy department gift
Transfer from department of Physics, 1989
- Series I: Arranged Correspondence
  - Subseries I.1: Chronological
    - , 1930s (Box 01, Folder 1-4)
    - Secretarial Miscellaneous, before 1963 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1930s (Box 02, Folder 1)
  - Subseries I.2: Subject
    - University Executive Council, 1942-1945 (Box 03, Folder 1)
    - University Office of Admissions, 1941-1955 (Box 03, Folder 2)
    - University-Public Ceremonies, 1943-1957 (Box 03, Folder 3)
    - Watson Laboratory, IBM Machine, 1940-1955 (Box 03, Folder 4)
    - Yale-Columbia Southern Station, 1951-1956 (Box 03, Folder 5)
    - George Pegram, 1940-1949 (Box 05, Folder 6)
    - Yale University Observatory, 1953-1962 (Box 03, Folder 7)
    - Yale-Columbia Southern Station, 1945-1951 (Box 03, Folder 8)
    - Stromgren, 1957-1958 (Box 04, Folder 1)
    - N.Y. Academy of Science, 1940-1945 (Box 04, Folder 2)
    - Office of Naval Research (ONR) (Box 04, Folder 3)
    - Oort, J.H., 1941-1960 (Box 04, Folder 4)
    - Neighbor's Society, 1937-1956 (Box 04, Folder 5)
    - Netherlands Book Committee, 1946 (Box 04, Folder 6)
    - Netherlands Information Bureau, 1941-1947 (Box 04, Folder 7)
    - Netherlands Study Group, 1945 (Box 04, Folder 8)
    - Netherlands University League, 1942-1950 (Box 04, Folder 11)
    - National Science Foundation (N.S.F.), 1953-1959 (Box 04, Folder 9)
    - A Punched Card Catalogue of Data for the Stars in the Boss General Catalogue (Box 04, Folder 10)
    - Mailing list, 1961-1962 (Box 04, Folder 12)
    - Netherlands Information Bureau, 1941-1947 (Box 04, Folder 10)
    - Struve, Werkes Observatory, 1934-1958 (Box 05, Folder 1)
    - Observatory Uccle, 1931-1946 (Box 05, Folder 2)
    - Schlesinger, 1940-1941 (Box 05, Folder 3)
    - Sydeny Observatory, 1953 (Box 05, Folder 4)
    - U.S. Naval Observatory, 1933-1959 (Box 05, Folder 5)
    - University of Brussels, 1946 (Box 05, Folder 6)
    - Osterhoff, P. - Holland, 1934-1951 (Box 05, Folder 7)
    - Polowe, David, 1942-1946 (Box 05, Folder 8)
    - Radcliffe Observatory, 1958 (Box 05, Folder 9)
    - Reuyl, D., 1942-1943 (Box 05, Folder 10)
    - Rosseland, 1945-1947 (Box 05, Folder 11)
    - Royal Observatory, 1946-1953 (Box 05, Folder 12)
    - Royal Observatory, South Africa, 1939-1957 (Box 05, Folder 13)
    - D.H. Sadler - Royal Greenwich Observatory, 1957-1959 (Box 05, Folder 14)
    - Schauer, Charles - Research Corporation, 1946-1949 (Box 05, Folder 15)
    - Prendergast, Kevin, 1953-1956 (Box 05, Folder 16)
    - Schwarzschild, M., 1941-1955 (Box 05, Folder 17)
    - Science Journal, 1940 (Box 05, Folder 18)
    - Shapley, Harlow, 1940-1957 (Box 05, Folder 19)
    - Sky and Telescope (Federer), 1942-1947 (Box 05, Folder 20)
    - Sproul Observatory - Swarthmore College, 1944-1956 (Box 05, Folder 21)
    - Dearborn Observatory - Northwestern University, 1940-1954 (Box 06, Folder 1)
    - de Vaucouleurs, G., 1953-1957 (Box 06, Folder 2)
    - Dunham, Theo, 1953-1954 (Box 06, Folder 3)
    - Eastman Kodak Co., 1941-1955 (Box 06, Folder 4)
    - Eckert, W., 1940-1957 (Box 06, Folder 5)
    - Eichner, L.C., 1946-1960 (Box 06, Folder 6)
    - Fulbright, J. - Australia, 1950-1959 (Box 06, Folder 7)
    - Geology Dept. - Columbia College, 1950-1953 (Box 06, Folder 8)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, 1959-1962 (Box 06, Folder 9)
    - Harvard College Observatory, 1939-1956 (Box 06, Folder 10)
    - Higgins Fund, 1954-1957 (Box 06, Folder 11)
    - Hill, Sarah J., 1947-1958 (Box 06, Folder 12)
    - Hill, Sarah - Makemson, Maud, 1934-1952 (Box 06, Folder 13)
    - International Astronomical Union (I.A.U.), 1950-1959 (Box 06, Folder 14)
    - Bok, Bart J., 1940-1957 (Box 07, Folder 1)
    - Brouwer, Dicr, 1955-1962 (Box 07, Folder 2)
    - Brouwer, Dirk, 1948-1955 (Box 07, Folder 3)
    - Astrophysical Journal, 1932-1949 (Box 07, Folder 4)
    - Barnard, 1942-1949 (Box 07, Folder 5)
    - Blaauw, Adrian, 1940-1958 (Box 07, Folder 6)
    - Bosscha Observatory, Hins, C.H., 1934-1946 (Box 07, Folder 7)
    - Bullen, K.E., 1953-1956 (Box 07, Folder 8)
    - Carnegie Institution of Washington, D.C., 1934-1960 (Box 07, Folder 9)
    - Cincinnati Observatory (Herget, P.), 1935-1959 (Box 07, Folder 10)
    - Curtiss-Wright Corporation, 1942-1943 (Box 07, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1958 (Box 08, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1951 (Box 08, Folder 2)
    - Menzel, Harvard Observatory, 1946-1954 (Box 08, Folder 3)
    - Johannesburg, South Africa, 1947-1957 (Box 08, Folder 4)
    - Johannesburg, South Africa - Photographic plates, 1947-1949 (Box 08, Folder 5)
    - Johannesburg, South African Embassy, 1949 (Box 08, Folder 6)
    - Mt. Stromlo, Canberra, Australia, 1949-1955 (Box 08, Folder 7)
    - Mt. Wilson and Palomar Observatories, 1931-1959 (Box 08, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1934-1947 (Box 08, Folder 9)
    - Princeton, 1940-1951 (Box 08, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, various dates (Box 08, Folder 11)
    - Star Tables, 1942-1950 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - University Notices, before 1963 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Teaching Assistant Records, 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Van de Kamp, 1940-1943 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Wachmann, A. - Visiting professor, 1959-1961 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Warner and Swasey Observatory, 1940-1956 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Washburn Observatory, 1947-1948 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Wood, Ben, 1933-1946 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Yale-Columbia Southern Observatory - Jackson, Cyril, 1959-1962 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Yale University Observatory, 1932-1950 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Yerkes Observatory, 1939-1950 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous (173) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Yowell, E.C., 1942-1955 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Science Committee, 1937-1945 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Secretarial Miscellaneous, Replies to Lay Inquiries, 1942-1956 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Argentina, Oct. 15, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Brouwer, Dirk, 1935-1945 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Brouwer, Dirk, 1945-1947 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1959 (Box 09, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, [v.d.] (Box 09, Folder 2)
- Series II: Committees and Course Materials
  - Budget, 1950-1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Personnel (Inactive), 1953-1956 (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Series III: Lab Materials
  - Research calculations, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Early Notes of Schilt
  - Early School Notes of Schilt (Box 25)
  - Chilean Report #2, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Budget, 1942-1949 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Columbia College, 1949-1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Columbia College, 1940-1949 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Faculty of Pure Science, 1940-1950 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - E.K.A. Fund, 1950-1954 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Instruction Minutes, 1947-1950 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Instruction - Faculty of Pure Science, 1940-1952 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Fellowships - Committee on Instruction - Faculty of Pure Science, 1954-1958 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - General Studies (G.S.), 1941-1957 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Graduate Students (Applicants), 1960-1962 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Graduate Students, 1947-1963 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Graduate Students, 1939-1961 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Students Records, 1943-1957 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Faculties, 1952-1961 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Hett, John, 1942 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Jacoby, Harold, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Library, 1940-1956 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Motz, L., 1960 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1933-1955 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Photometry - (Glass Filter), 1946-1954 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Rejected Manuscripts, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Salary statements, 1947-1961 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Old Clark Telescopes, 1950-1951 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 69 - Writings by Schilt, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 69-Writings by Schilt, 1939-1941 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - 56-Writings by Schilt, 1950 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Notes; Research Materials, 1950s & 1960s (Box 14)
  - Photometer Paper, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Distribution of Stars According to Apparent Magnitudes & Galatic Latitude and the Scale of the Polar Sequence by Jan Schilt, circa 1946 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sodium Line Intensities as Criterion for Stellar Distances by Jan Schilt, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Conference Remarks - Ms. & Correspondence, 1957 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - The Astronomical Journal, 1940-1958 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Sub-Committee for Inter-American Astronomy, 1959-1962 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - American Astronomical Society (AAS), 1941-1962 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1928-1949 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - The American Association of Variable Star Observers (AAVSO), 1954 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Allegheny Observatory, 1941-1955 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - American Astronomical Society, 1950-1960 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Askania-Werks, 1950-1951 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Kapetyn Astronomical Lab, 1947-1957 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Leander McCormick Observatory - University of Virginia, 1940-1958 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    [Schilt's correspondence]
  - Lick Observatory, 1940-1941 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Linblad, Bertil, 1934-1951 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    [Correspondence]
  - Luyten, W.J., 1931-1948 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - 69 - Writings by Schilt, 1940s - 1950s (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Note on the Colors of the AoP Stars - Writing by Schilt, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Photoelectric Color 2036 Stars - Writing by Schilt & others, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 69-Writings by Schilt and others, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - 69-Research Materials and Notes, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Minor Cloud "B". Plate 59312 (Blue), undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    [Research calculations]
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Plate 61626 (Center-Red), undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Center Plate 61834 (Red), undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Minor Cloud "B". Summary, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Experiment 2, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Experiment 0-4, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - GS Astronomy 1, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Stennbs Experiments I, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Experiments O, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Experiment 0-5, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Stencils; Assignments, Observing Lists, Stars & Constellations, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Experiment I-10, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Experiment I-1, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Experiment I-8, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Experiment O-2, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Experiment O-3, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Experiment I-8, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Experiment I-7, undated (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Experiment O-10, undated (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - Research Calculations, 1949-1950 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Research Notes, undated (Box 18)
  - Table 1 - The Equation of Time, undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Reading List of G.S. Ast. I, undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Problem Lists, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Mechanics Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - E.C.X. - Research Calculations, undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Astronomy 1 - Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Astronomy 115 & R55, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography - Astronomy 116, undated+ (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 89-Research Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - School of Mines - Spherical Astronomy Notes, undated (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Experiment I-13, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Experiment O-9, 1946 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Experiment O-8, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Experiment O-7, 1948 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Experiment I-11, 1949-1950 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Laboratory Assignments - Astronomy 1, 1949-1950 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Observing List - Astronomy 1, 1949-1950 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - G.S. Astronomy 2, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Astronomy Class Lab Experiments, undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Blue Center, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Minor Cloud "B" - PL 59 v 91 - Center Blue, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
    [Research Calculations]
  - Field Corrections, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Calculations and an article from "Astronomical Journal", 1947 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - C61505 (2 hr. exposure), 1st Measure, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Research calculations, undated (Box 21, Folder 7-18)
  - Comparison with Other Catalogues, undated (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Zone +20 to +25, undated (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - Zone +25 to +30, undated (Box 21, Folder 21)
  - Zone +50 - +55, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Zone +55 - +60, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous - All Zones, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Notes and memos, 1950s (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Stencil-blank forms for research, undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Atomic Bomb Committee, November 1945 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    [Memos and drafts of letters]
  - Budget, 1961-1962 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Minor Cloud B - Offsets-New Lists & Measurements, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Comparison of Readings with Different Backgrounds & Different D-2 Openings, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Comparison, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Comparison of Iris Readings Made By Turning Wheel Clockwise & Counterclockwise, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Measurments of..., undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Minor Cloud B - Offset Plates - Work Done with Preliminary Lists, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Title of Chart Sent to Zurich, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 23, Folder 9-18)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
  - Budget Correspondence, 1940s (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Appointments (Forms, etc. Prior to 1962) (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Accounts - Old Correspondence, 1941-1955 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Research Calculations, undated (Box 24, Folder 7-8)
- Series V: Testing Materials
  - Various Locations (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Site Report, Australia, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Chilean Site Testing, 1959 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) Balance Sheets, 1960 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Observation, El Leoncito, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Argentina: Finance Administration, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - El Leoncito Final Copy & Correspondence, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Leoncito - Data, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Chilean Correspondence, 1959 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Astrograph Construction, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Sites-Chile, 1958-1961 (Box 27, Folder 4)
  - Site Photographs (Box 27, Folder 5)
  - Tucson Report - Chile Report, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 6)
  - NSF G-8165 - Financial, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - NSF - G-8165, 1957-1963 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Trip to Australia, 1958-1959 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - NSF - G-8165 on Budget, Grants, 1959-1962 (Box 27, Folder 10)
  - Site Reports, to J. Oort, 1962-1963 (Box 27, Folder 11)
  - Site-testing, Australia, South Africa, 1956-1958 (Box 27, Folder 12)
  - Trips to South America, 1959-1961 (Box 27, Folder 13)
  - Ford Foundation, 1959-1960 (Box 27, Folder 14)
  - Astro - Plans and Correspondence - New Telescope, 1960 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    [Photographs included]